Alejandro Rodriguez Orama

LinkedIn | Github | Portfolio | +1 (519) 991-7324

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:

A problem-solving-oriented Data Analyst with 6+ years of experience, a bachelor's degree in mathematics, and a postgraduate degree in Data Analytics for Business from St. Clair College, Canada, where he achieved a perfect 4.0 GPA and received the Faculty Academic Award 2023. He has extensive experience in data analytics, statistical analysis, and machine learning, and Alejandro's projects showcase his proficiency in Python, R, and SQL. His project achievements include leading innovative solutions in recycling optimization and winning 1st place in the Deep Learning and Computer Vision for Autonomous Vehicles 2023 Future Mobility Challenge.

SKILLS:

- Programming: Python, R, SQL, SPSS
- Libraries\Frameworks: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn, ggplot, tidyverse, tidymodels, shiny, markdown.
- BI Tools: Microsoft Excel, Tableau, Power BI, Power Automate.

EXPERIENCE:

Researcher Intern, St. Clair College

Windsor, Ontario | July 2022 - July 2023

- Created and managed the REDCap database for the 1000 Books Before Kindergarten project in Windsor, designing data entry forms and surveys for pre-test and post-test research.
- Monitored data quality and performed quality control checks, significantly improving data accuracy and enabling more precise measurement of the project's impact on early childhood literacy.
- Developed a descriptive data analysis report with user-friendly graphics to visualize survey results, making complex data more accessible and interpretable for stakeholders and the project manager.

Data Collection Analyst PFF FC

Remote Windsor, Ontario | March 2022 - Jul 2022

- Worked with the PFF FC's data collection system collecting statistics from soccer games.
- PFF's On the Ball soccer data collection.

Statistical Analyst, National Statistics Office

Havana, Cuba | September 2015 - October 2021

- Designed and developed survey methodologies, and applied sampling and data collection strategies for household surveys.
- Managed and analyzed large datasets to identify trends and patterns, evaluate missing data, and find outliers.
- Performed statistical analysis, compiled contingency tables, and applied tests for statistical significance using software such as R and SPSS.
- Prepare detailed reports and presentations to communicate findings to stakeholders like the Oxford Poverty methodology for measuring multidimensional poverty.
- Coded and automated data validation rules using R cutting the data validation time by 80% and improving data quality
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to provide data-driven insights and ensure data quality and integrity through rigorous validation and cleaning processes.

EDUCATION:

- Post-graduation degree in Data Analytics for Business, St. Clair College

- Bachelor's degree in Mathematics, University of Havana

Windsor, Canada | May 2022 - August 2023 Havana, Cuba | September 2011 - July 2015

PROJECTS:

Recycling Collection Service | Read More

Python, Plotly, Pandas, PostgreSQL, Roboflow

- Used TensorFlow to fine-tune pre-trained models like MobileNet, EfficientDet Lite, and YOLOv5 on a custom database to detect recycling objects. It then leverages geolocation data extracted from these images, storing the image metadata in a PostgreSQL database.

Computer Vision for Autonomous Vehicles | Read More

Tensorflow, Pandas, Matplotlib

- Trained and evaluated several convolutional neural network architectures, and applied fine-tuned and transfer learning to pre-trained models like VGG16 and ResNet V2 to classify traffic sign images.

Exploring EV population in Washington | Read More

tableau, data story, dashboards, dynamic visualization, KPIs

- Designed a tableau story to explore the growth rate of EV cars in Washington State. Provided insights using relevant KPIs and powerful dashboards.

Financial Analysis Report (Amazon case) | Read More

Seasonality and Trend Analysis, Monte Carlo Simulation

- A detailed financial analysis of Amazon, utilizing the Monte Carlo simulation and financial modeling to forecast stock price movements and evaluate financial health. Provided strategic recommendations based on key metrics that drive informed decisions for future investment and operational decisions.

CERTIFICATIONS:

- Career Essentials in Data Analysis by Microsoft and LinkedIn Show credential
- Datacamp track Data Analyst in SQL Show credential
- Datacamp track Data Analyst with R Show credential

PUBLICATIONS:

- National Population Aging Survey 2017. Results obtained, 2017 <u>Link</u>
- National Migration Survey 2016 Link